[screaming]
[theme music playing]
[Yusuf] The troops are quartered.
Burial preparations are underway
for those we were able to retrieve.
I have ordered scouting parties to sweep
the grasslands a week's ride away
in case Sidao is...
audacious enough
to siege Cambulac.
Finally, we are conscripting
new troops from the north.
I have begun preparations for training.
I fear they may be less compliant now,
but we shall do what is necessary
to bend the willful.
My Lord.
Is that truly all?
Do you not wish to discuss your counsel?
And my disregard of it?
The Polo matter,
are you prepared to proceed?
[Yusuf] Master Marco,
in his infinite wisdom and compassion,
the Khan of Khans grants you
a final audience to plead for mercy.
[Marco] I will not plead for mercy.
But I will defend myself.
May I seek clarity as to
the charges levied against me?
[Jingim] Treason.
[Ahmad] I take no pleasure in this,
Master Marco.
But it seems great misfortune
has descended upon our kingdom
on your arrival.
I did not choose to remain here.
I chose to be released to my father.
[Ahmad] Your time in the Kochkor region.
Your ability to enter and leave
without repercussion.
And do you suspect Byamba,
son of the Khan,
to have blood on his hands?
We traveled side by side.
Is that accurate, Byamba?
Were you always at the Latin's side
on your journey?
I was asked to be here and I came.
But you cannot compel me
to be party to this.
[grunts sharply]
No, we were not side by side.
There was a point where
he was negotiating for my life
while I sat captive,
preparing to die.
And if I remember,
you sent the Latin with me on my journey.
After he convinced me to do so.
How does your body
stand straight without a spine?
[Ahmad] Xiangyang.
The loss.
Your journey there.
Your time with the whore's whore-friend.
Sanctioned by the Khan of Khans.
You alerted the Song
to our pending attack.
You conspired to lead us
into the slaughter.
What need would they of warning?
They knew we were descending
at a week's distance.
As to the wall...
I am guilty.
I founder in the blood of the thousands
who perished for my error.
I have no defense.
But right or wrong, I have done nothing
but serve my captor and Khan.
And only him?
Yes.
Is that all?
Nothing you have presented is punishable
by the laws of the Khan of Khans.
[Jingim] I had this translated.
Would you care to share with the Khan
the words that you keep
so closely to your still-beating heart?
"All kings shall fall before him."
[Jingim] "All kings...
shall fall before him."
It was a gift.
[Jingim] From father to son?
[Marco] Yes.
A verse from the scriptures of a religion
welcomed, like all the others,
within the walls of Cambulac.
A faith with designs on our kingdom.
I know nothing of that.
But I do believe
you have designs on the Vatican.
What of it?
Respectfully, Lord Khan...
we reap what we sow.
You speak recklessly.
I speak honestly.
You deserve honesty.
You believe I should not conquer the West?
On the contrary, Lord Khan.
The most common law
of nature and of man...
is to take what has been mandated
by God
or by the swords and arrows you command.
You claim both.
But you must be prepared
for the resistance of the lionhearted.
And the West is not weak.
Have you nothing more to say
to champion your cause?
It seems my end is guaranteed
no matter what words I sound.
Indeed.
Mmm.
[inhaling]
The Imperial Seal is yours, Chancellor.
And with it, the dynasty.
Chancellor... even still?
Unless your birthright has altered.
The Seven Families are arriving.
Songs of your victory
have carried far and wide.
How you eviscerated the Mongol horde,
body and soul.
They are prepared
to pledge their fealty to the Emperor.
They're going to want to see the boy.
That is assured.
[Jia Sidao] No one truly believes
the boy guides his own hand.
Yet the sheep elevate him.
I must stand behind him.
A wise tactic, my Chancellor.
I suppose I couldn't simply
imprint this on his skull
and float him down the Yangtze?
[Kokachin] Tell me your name.
You need not fear me.
It is Judar, my Princess.
You may call me Kokachin.
No, Princess.
Do you defy me?
In this, I do.
If you defy this simple request,
how am I to know
you will not defy a greater one?
The truest of servants
knows our needs better than we do.
Leave us.
I was your age
when I was promised to Kublai.
It was terrifying.
I knew he would be Khan
even if he himself did not.
At the time...
I felt as if I was unworthy,
that a mistake had surely been made
and at a moment's notice
someone would unveil me as a fraud.
It was not until Kublai's mother
gifted me this,
the finest of silks, to be woven
into my presentational gown,
that I knew it was true.
I kept what remained
to one day gift to a daughter of my own.
It is lovely.
A mere reflection of the beauty
who wears it.
I also come to pay condolences
and to inquire as to your heart.
I lost a good friend.
Your only friend, if I recall.
I hope it's no longer the case,
my Queen.
If you speak of me...
speak with certainty.
I'm afraid loss has infected
the kingdom of late.
With more on the horizon.
So I've heard.
You've heard?
The Latin is to be executed.
At dawn.
A seamstress will pay you a visit shortly.
[sighs deeply]
[Jingim] Master Polo.
I came to inquire
as to your state of mind.
My thanks for your concern, Jingim.
Prince.
[Marco] Prince Jingim.
[snickers]
[Jingim] I know this seems unjust,
and it's hard for you to see,
sitting where you are.
But understand... that this is entirely
for the good of the kingdom.
Do you hunt?
In our culture, your first hunt,
as in many things in life,
is a very lonely enterprise.
You're cast into the wilderness
with nothing more than a bow and an arrow
and instructed not to return without meat.
For the kingdom.
It can take a day, a week.
Some never return.
What do you think is the most vital trait
for the hunter to possess?
Please, Jingim,
do not mar my final hours.
Patience.
I saw its horns first.
Grand, stretching to the heavens
and catching the morning light.
A mighty trophy.
I set my arrow, took aim.
He was gone.
But I had a feeling about him...
and so I waited another night.
It was so cold,
I wanted to run home.
A handful of kills passed me by.
I could have slain them all,
returned triumphant,
dipped my finger in the fat of the kill,
been deemed a man
and slept in my own bed.
But I waited.
As I felt the sun warm me
the next morning...
there it was,
passing between the trees.
My father was so proud.
Patience.
Patience to ensure that
true aim finds the true target.
An innocent target,
whose offense was crossing paths
at the wrong time,
with the wrong person.
Death.
Another lonely enterprise.
May your God accompany you,
Master Polo.
You will need it more than I.
[Jia Sidao] Let us not build strife
where none should exist.
Pride and hope have filled
the coffers of the people's spirits.
Those coffers were never depleted.
You simply convinced yourself otherwise
to support your own machinations.
[Jia Sidao] Why am I your enemy
when you're the one prepared to bury
our culture in history's potter's field?
The landed gentry of the south
prepare to meet.
Are these the same landed gentry
whose land you stripped
against my husband's wishes
not long ago?
The proceeds from the fields
helped fund our defenses.
And each now pledges their support
for an assault on Cambulac.
My compliments, Jia Sidao.
[Jia Sidao] Insincerity still.
I am nothing but sincere.
You set out to undermine the council
and retain the chancellorate.
Fang Zhen fell.
You sought to repel the Mongol horde
and masterfully lured them into
a hornet's nest of sharpened steel.
You wish to gather Southern China
into one indomitable force
and gird them for the final unification.
I have no doubt
you will succeed in that as well.
But you will do so without the support
you are about to ask of me.
How might I convince you
of the folly of your decision?
Stop tinkering with that
and look at me.
There is nothing
you might say or do.
Ever.
I assumed that
would be your answer.
Very well.
I shall go it alone.
Yet again.
[Empress Dowager] You need the Emperor
in order to accomplish your final design.
You cannot lock me
away from him forever.
[Jia Sidao] My dear Empress...
I never considered that an option.
-[gun fires]
-[body thudding]
[grunting]
You're here to defend him?
Lord Khan, years ago,
you took my eyes.
Today... I offer you the rest of me.
What do you speak of?
If the boy is culpable as you say,
and I have no reason to doubt
the Khan's good judgment on such matters,
then I am equally culpable.
You entrusted the Latin to me.
I trained him, fought beside him.
How can you not
believe me complicit?
-Get out!
-Lord Khan--
Guards!
Escort the monk out of my sight.
Do not allow him to return.
-Where do you intend to go?
-The Ministry of Justice.
-For what purpose?
-None of your concern.
My apologies,
but you may not leave, Princess.
Pardon me?
I cannot allow you to leave.
You're my servant.
As well as your defender.
Whom do you take orders from?
The Blue Princess commands me
as dictated by the Great Khan.
You had best remember that.
Stand aside!
Empress Chabi has instructed
that you remain in your quarters.
-Until?
-We receive further orders.
Hello, Ling Ling.
I appreciate your regard, child,
but sit with me.
You're beyond your years
in grace and training.
Regrettably, that is found
far too infrequently in children your age.
My thanks, My Lady.
When I was a young girl,
my mother told me it was as if
I had been raised by wild yaks,
spitting and kicking
everyone around me.
How are you feeling?
My feet hurt less, My Lady.
Good news.
How are you finding
your time in Cambulac?
I enjoy it greatly.
You miss your home?
Your family?
Tell me of your mother.
To have a daughter such as yourself,
she must be lovely.
She is. She's a dancer.
A dancer?
Does she dance for you?
For my father.
I am quite sure he enjoys that.
She was his favorite.
His favorite?
Did your father
have many dancers?
Does your father still live?
Did your father sit on a throne?
[Ahmad] We own Chinese royalty?
That's more precious than anything
that surrounds us in this moment.
The question is,
how best to use it?
We own nothing.
The daughter rightfully does not trust me.
The mother less so.
Her mother's like a wounded animal,
desperate for kindness.
One which will lick your hand
simply to get a taste before biting.
Some men pay good coin
for such pleasures.
I wonder sometimes
about that mind of yours.
Clear in intent, Lady Empress.
Then be intent on this matter.
To tame an animal,
it must fear the raising of your hand.
I may be just ahead of you
at this moment.
How so?
I planted a seed in the mother's head
that her daughter is...
closer than she first envisioned.
I imagine it may have
sprouted as a weed.
Hmm.
[Marco] I value your friendship, Sifu.
As I have stated time and again,
I am not your friend.
Far from it.
I know you wish to believe that,
but you cared for me,
taught me, protected me.
What would you call that,
if not friendship?
An onerous burden.
In few hours' time,
that burden will be lifted.
[Hundred Eyes]
And I will have lost a friend.
[Marco] Is there no escape?
[Hundred Eyes]
From you leaving this mortal body?
[Marco] Yes.
[Hundred Eyes] None.
Unless you can find
something to gift to him
that is more valuable than your life.
[thunder rumbling]
[Zhao Xian] Why?
[Jia Sidao]
She missed your father so much.
Sometimes, hearts are broken
and they cannot be pieced together again.
Will mine break?
No... because you do not need her.
You do not need me or anyone.
You need only this.
What do you see?
A bug.
You're most correct,
but it is so much more.
This mantis that I give to you
was one of 300 nymphs, babies...
about this big.
Imagine that, 300.
The strongest among them
kill the weakest among them
until the very best are left.
A mere handful.
Now, this mantis will leave this life
within 10 months of today.
You must take this time as an opportunity
to learn everything you can.
To study, to practice,
to absorb all the lessons of the mantis,
for there are many.
Patience, speed,
adaptability, ruthlessness.
The traits of a warrior king.
Heed my words, my Emperor...
and you will become as the mantis.
[Kokachin] Judar?
Yes, Princess?
Fetch me some sandalwood
for my bath.
Yes, Princess.
[gasps]
[panting]
What are your thoughts?
I do not know.
Is it my doing?
Are you frustrated with me?
No. No, never.
I need you here.
I am.
Why am I not relieved?
You are sensitive to the grief of others,
no matter their transgressions.
Every breath the Latin takes
is a burden on your soul.
At sun's light... you will find relief.
Did I introduce a curse
into our bed?
You are the son of a Khan...
a Khan in waiting.
The fault rests with me
and me alone.
[door opening]
[Chabi] Do not make your presence known.
I wanted you to see that she lives.
As you wished.
She will always be here,
under my watchful eye,
under my tutelage.
I will care for her as my own.
[gasps]
Look at her, remember her.
You will never see her again.
But if you do what I say,
when I say it,
you can be secure in the knowledge that
her days will stretch long before her.
Come now.
What is the benefit
of being a princess
if your lord requires you
to perform your own labor?
We will do the same
to our children one day.
Where are your belongings?
I looked for what I should pack
and realized everything I need is here.
In a week's time, we will be home.
Is this as foreign to you
as it is to me?
More so.
Do you think we will ever settle into it?
I hope not.
Minister.
Is this what you
summoned me down here for?
You oversee war.
And I am going to tell you how to win it.
Thank you for coming.
Do you think I would deny
a dying man an audience?
I know nothing of you.
In this, you are at a decided advantage.
Your journal.
It is most enlightening
when one has unfettered access
inside a person's thoughts.
Warrantless access.
To be fair, you were an enigma.
One that had grown close to my Khan.
You could have sat with me
prior to my last night of life...
and asked.
I am certain you would not have granted me
the insight I required.
But...
I procured the journal
prior to your writing of one curiosity.
What made you cease
your attempts at escape?
Was it her?
Under the circumstances,
you need not hold your tongue.
Partially.
Significantly.
But not entirely.
Tell me.
The walled Phoenician city of Tyre.
It defied Alexander for 13 long years.
Built on an island,
Tyre was walled to the sea,
an insurmountable fortress
that was key to all of Persia.
He attempted to breach the walls
using common instruments of war,
arrows, battering rams, catapults.
But three dozen men
are needed to load and fire one.
Alexander employed... the trebuchet,
a siege engine powered not by men
but by a counterweight.
Imagine the weight of
6,000 pounds on one end
and a 300-pound rock set on the other.
Imagine firing 1,000 in a single day.
Imagine what even three of these engines
could do to the walls of Xiangyang.
And at a distance that keeps
the army safe from archers.
Correct.
Altruism still?
Even in the face of your execution?
Not purely.
I'm not afraid to die...
but I'm terrified to do so
while branded a traitor.
What is the entirety you spoke of earlier?
What else made you stay?
The moment the Khan gave me the choice
to deliver my father from death.
He is a good man.
Grandfather, why couldn't
you have taken that?
Why couldn't you have taken that wall?
My Emperor, these men
are all that remain of the Red Lotus.
Traitors within the kingdom determined
to undermine the Emperor's mission,
determined to destroy
the Emperor and his dynasty.
They are your enemy.
They are weak.
They must be punished.
What does the strong mantis do
to its weaker brothers and sisters?
Kill them.
[Jia Sidao] Hmm.
A catapult?
Waste of my time.
Lord Khan, with respect,
this may very well be the key--
[Kublai] The key to Xiangyang, finally!
If only my Vice Regent
had attained this key years ago!
Some magical solution?
Why did you bring this to me
when I know you crave my failure?
If that is what you believe,
then you have not
been listening to anything--
[Kublai] Enough of your insolence!
You...
beg for my pardon,
is that your scheme?
No, Sire.
Begging is for the guilty.
I've seen stronger men than you
weep before the rug.
When the time comes,
be brave and sure.
For it is coming at dawn...
no matter how loud you cry.
-Lord Khan--
-[grunts sharply]
[Kublai slurping]
[breathes deeply]
[Kublai] Liar!
You're a liar!
Remove yourself.
We speak of this lunacy no more.
Tell the kheshig to jail me.
You made your point, take your leave.
There is honest work to be done.
This is merely a statement of facts.
Oh! You hired the assassins?
You manipulated that whore, Mei Lin.
You instructed my brother
to withhold his troops from Wuchang?
You conspired with Jia Sidao?
I conspired for and with the Khanate.
And you think, what?
The Khanate does not guide my heart?
Your mind.
But minds can be easily
persuaded of anything.
The reason you do not sleep
is because of a longing in your heart
-that will never be sated.
-And why should it?
-I know you believe Xiangyang will fall.
-It will.
And you fear that once conquered,
I turn my aims to lands far reaching?
-I do.
-[shouting] Why should I not?
Because you know how this will end.
As all other dynasties have.
Am I not different?
I once believed so.
It is why I stand before you this evening.
Yusuf, you did not do this.
My confession stands.
Be it betrayal by my hands
or by my heart,
I am guilty.
What do you want from me?
To give up Xiangyang?
-You know the answer is yes.
-I cannot.
I know that as well.
I should hide behind my wall?
Take pleasure in the present state?
While away my days
and bury myself here when they're done?
Where is the fault in that? Hmm?
How many lands must be reaped?
How many vaults must be filled
and young spirits extinguished?
One. One last game.
Taken the pieces away.
The boy is guilty.
His only guilt
is his blind desire for your love.
You know who he reminds me of?
Yusuf... my crazed cripple of Khazaria.
Not in mindless bloodletting...
but in dedication to your cause.
He does.
You need that dedication
at your service
at all times.
I am no longer capable of it,
nor am I willing.
You have the finest engineers
in all the world.
My final counsel to you
is that you put them to work.
Construct the Latin's siege engine.
As your Khan,
I do not accept your confession.
I have sent messages to every corner of
the kingdom outlining my complicity.
In doing so, I have weakened your position
before Karakorum and throughout China.
You will be challenged in the Kurultai.
You will lose.
And in that...
a dream of this place may endure.
You have no choice, Kublai.
[birds chirping]
[inhales deeply]
I thought I had until dawn.
The final battle looms.
Be decisive in your victory.
You are released from this prison.
But I am truly free.
[man shouting faintly]
[horses galloping]
[man urging horse]
[theme music playing]